（汉斯顿公馆 1542年）
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth!
- 玛丽女士 - 伊丽莎白
- Lady Mary. - Elizabeth!
你梳妆完毕了吗
Are you dressed?
还未 我在看书
Not quite. I was reading.
过来坐下 我有个喜讯
Come and sit. I have some news.
- 玛丽 是何喜讯 - 我刚听说
- Mary, what is it? - I just heard!
根据议会法案
By Act of Parliament you and I are.
你我都恢复了继承权
both restored to the succession.
当然 是排在爱德华及其继承人之后
After Edward and his heirs, of course.
一定是国王主动提出
The King himself must have commanded this.
你不为此而高兴吗 伊丽莎白
Are you not pleased, Elizabeth?
想想这意味着什么
Think what this means.
我很高兴 玛丽
Yes, Mary.
你若高兴 那我也高兴
If you are pleased then so am I.
这意味着 国王仍爱着我们
It means that the King loves both of us.
还意味着你也许某天会成为女王
And that you may be Queen some day.
你也一样 伊丽莎白女王
And you. Queen Elizabeth.
伊丽莎白
Elizabeth?
怎么了
What's wrong?
鉴于发生在
Because of what happened.
凯瑟琳王后身上的一切 我已下定决心
to Queen Katherine, I have made my mind up.
什么决心
In what?
上帝作证
As God is my witness,
我将永不成婚
I shall never marry!
绝不
Never!
陛下 罗马大使阁下到
Your Majesty, His Excellency the Imperial Ambassador.
- 大使阁下 - 陛下
- Excellency. - Your Majesty.
陛下真是友好周到
Your Majesty is most gracious.
相信陛下已经得知
I am sure Your Majesty is aware.
我主罗马皇帝正与法兰西国王再度交战
my master, the Emperor, is once more at war with King Francis.
法兰西国王厚颜无耻 竟与土耳其勾结
The French King's despicable alliance with the Turk.
这不仅危及罗马边境
threatens not only the borders of the Emperor's domains,
也威胁到了整个欧洲的安全
but also the security of the whole of Europe.
因此
For that reason alone,
皇帝陛下命我前来
his Imperial Majesty has asked me.
再度向陛下您伸出友谊之手
to offer the hand of friendship to Your Majesty once more,
请您与我们结盟
in joint alliance.
共克背信弃义的法兰西
against the perfidious French.
我有何好处
What would I gain?
您可收回所有失地
All your lost territories.
外加整个阿基坦地区（法国西南部）
The whole of Aquitaine.
大使阁下 请便
Excellency.
莱斯利
Risley!
大使阁下 陛下有请
Excellency.
法兰西大使阁下到
His Excellency the French Ambassador.
- 马里亚克先生 - 陛下
- Monsieur Marillac. - Your Majesty.
我听闻贵国正与罗马皇帝交战
I hear your country is at war… with the Emperor.
确有此事
Indeed.
罗马皇帝违背了
The Emperor has broken all his promises.
当日对法兰西国王及陛下您
and treaty obligations,
所做的承诺 并违反了盟约
both to my master King Francis and to you.
马里亚克先生
Monsieur Marillac,
当日你签署缔结条约时
when you signed a treaty, your master agreed to pay.
贵国国王曾答应为我国支付年恤金
an annual pension to this country,
但过去两年他都借口拖延
which he has defaulted on for the past two years.
因此 他至今已欠下了白银白万两
As a consequence, he now owes arrears of a million crowns.
陛下 若果真如此
Majesty, if that is true…
你是在质疑我的话吗 马里亚克先生
You doubt my word, Monsieur Marillac?
那么
Then…
我会禀明国王陛下
His Majesty will be informed.
所欠款项定当随后送来
And redress will surely follow.
十多年来 我们两国的结盟
The alliance between our countries has kept.
一直平衡着欧洲的势力
the balance of power in Europe for over ten years.
如今 面对罗马帝国的入侵
Surely Your Majesty would not care.
相信陛下
to compromise that arrangement now,
定无意破坏盟约吧
in the face of Imperial aggression?
马里亚克先生
Monsieur Marillac.
你即刻修书一封 告诉苏格兰国王
I want you to write a letter to the King of the Scots.
我国邀请他
Tell him that we invite him.
签署一份协议 明确我国的宗主权
to sign a treaty acknowledging our suzerainty.
并要求他立刻解除
over his country. Also to tell him to stop.
与法国以及教皇的联盟 否则后果自负
his French and Papal alliances, or suffer the consequences.
- 遵命 陛下 - 大人 你即刻前往苏格兰
- Majesty. - My Lord, I want you to prepare to go to Scotland.
确保我外甥接受这份协议
in case my cousin refuses to concede to our demands.
- 遵命 陛下 - 带萨里同去
- Majesty. - And take Surrey with you.
你的牌技真是精湛 李先生
You play very well, Mr. Leigh.
此乃浪费生命的表现
Always the sign of a wasted life.
你我身上的共同之处
You know, you and I have more in common.
远比你想象得多 大人
than you might imagine, my Lord.
- 愿闻其详 - 我们的家族
- What? - Our families.
都来自斯托克韦尔的圣玛丽教区
both come from St. Mary's parish in Stockwell.
教堂也是在同一年建立
and our chapels were founded in the same year.
泛泛之论 实难苟同 李先生
That hardly makes us equal, Mr. Leigh.
还有一样
There is another thing.
我的家族与前皇后也沾亲带故
Like you, my family was related to the late Queen.
你不觉得在宫廷里议论死者有失妥当吗
Do not you think it unseemly to raise her ghost at court?
我认为有失妥当的是
I think it unseemly.
你们霍华德见其行荒淫之事
that you Howards turned a blind eye.
竟然不闻不问 不管不顾
to her despicable wantonness,
致使吾等受其牵连 败坏名声
which tarnished the reputations of all of us associated with her!
「你们霍华德」
"You Howards!"
你方才是这样说的吧
Is that what you just said?
「你们霍华德」
"You Howards"?
守卫
Guards!
我要割下你的舌头 神定助我
I'll cut your tongue out, so help me God!
我要割下你那该死的舌头
I'll cut your fucking tongue out!
放开我
Get off me!
拉蒂默大人
Lord Latimer,
托马斯·西摩爵士来访
Sir Thomas Seymour.
是托马斯爵士啊
Oh. Sir Thomas,
你能来真好
how good of you to come.
请原谅 我身体不适
Please… Please forgive my infirmities.
如您所见 我状况欠佳
As you can see, I am not a well man.
相信阁下很快就能恢复
I trust your Lordship will soon recover.
恐怕我是难以康复如初了
I am afraid my health is too far broken to be mended.
请允许我介绍我的妻子
Ah! Allow me to present my wife,
凯瑟琳·帕尔 来见过托马斯·西摩爵士
Catherine Parr. Catherine, Sir Thomas Seymour.
拉蒂默夫人
Lady Latimer.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas.
请坐 托马斯爵士
Please. Sit down, Sir Thomas.
托马斯爵士 我不知道
Sir Thomas, I do not know.
您是否清楚我的个人经历
if you are aware of my personal history?
拉蒂默是北部地区的古老家族
The Latimers are an old northern family.
不幸的是
and, unfortunately, we were.
那次起兵造反 我们作为叛党被俘
caught up in the late Rebellion against His Majesty.
罗伯特·阿斯克把我当做人质
I myself was taken hostage by Robert Aske.
关押起来 百般羞辱
and sore constrained by him.
陛下令我拒绝向阿斯克认罪
His Majesty demanded that I reject Aske which I did,
并前往伦敦归顺于他
and came to London to submit to him.
但叛国罪名犹如达摩克利斯之剑
Still I think the shadow of treason hangs over me and my family.
我知道国王对您信任有加
I know you have the ear of the King.
我希望您替我在陛下面前
I would like you to make submission.
美言几句
on my behalf to His Majesty,
转达我绝对的忠诚…
of my utter loyalty and… and…
别说了 亲爱的
There, my darling.
闭上眼睛休息片刻
Close your eyes and rest now.
托马斯爵士
Sir Thomas.
他是否有所察觉
Do you think he suspects anything?
不 没有 我敢肯定
No. Nothing. I'm sure of it.
他将不久于人世 凯瑟琳
He cannot be long for this world, Catherine.
- 别说这样的话 - 我的意思是
- Hush! Don't say such things. - I only meant.
我等不及与你厮守 结为夫妻
that I cannot wait until we can be together, and married.
天地可鉴
As truly as God is God,
我万分期待与你结婚
I desire to marry you above all others.
萨里伯爵给陛下的议会写了封信
The Earl of Surrey has written a letter to Your Majesty's Council.
伯爵目前关押在弗利特监狱
The Earl is presently detained at the Fleet Prison.
监狱 所为何事
Prison? What for?
据说他与李约翰
It seems he was in an affray.
在宫中发生争执
with one John Leigh within the verge of the court.
被警卫官逮捕
and was arrested by the Sergeant-at-Arms.
因何事争执
What was the cause of the quarrel?
必是言语之间折损了萨里伯爵的颜面
I believe it touched upon his Lordship's pride.
- 他在信中说什么 - 他要求立刻出狱
- What does he write? - He demands his immediate release.
- 你有否答复 - 我们告诉伯爵大人
- Have you replied? - We informed his Lordship.
如此狂妄自大
that his lack of humility.
只能适得其反 难以如愿
would only impair his prospects of liberty.
他凭什么认定该被释放
And why does he say he should be released?
他暗示萨里伯爵此等人物
He infers that the Earl of Surrey has.
不应遭受这般待遇
no business being so treated in the first place.
还说不负陛下所托 必将全力讨贼
He also speaks of his readiness to serve Your Majesty on active duty.
在我看来 全英格兰最傲慢的蠢货非他莫属
I think he is the most foolish proud man in all of England.
让他为日后行为支付高额担保 然后释放
Set a high surety on his future behaviour, but release him.
我要派他去苏格兰
I want him in Scotland.
（苏格兰）
什么苏格兰人的骄傲 见鬼去吧
Go on with your Scottish pride!
萨里大人 这是三位被俘的贵族
My Lord Surrey, here are three of their nobles.
卡西里斯大人 格兰凯恩大人
captured in battle: Lord Cassilis, Lord Glencairn,
和麦斯威尔大人
and Lord Maxwell.
大人们
My Lords,
我们将依据身份与地位的不同
you will be treated with the honour and respect.
以礼相待
due to your rank and station.
以国王亨利八世之名
In the name of His Majesty, King Henry VIII,
我邀请诸位随我返回伦敦
I invite you to return with us to London,
在那里能得到最好的安置
where you will be most comfortably housed.
不过 你们必须先弃剑投降
However, I must ask you to surrender your swords.
过来照顾这些马匹 带些绳子来
Come with those horses and bring the rope!
大人们 索维莫斯一战 我军大获全胜
My Lords, a great victory was had by us at Solway Moss.
这全归功于赫福德大人和萨里大人
Thanks to my Lord Hertford and to my Lord Surrey,
几位苏格兰贵族被俘
several Scottish nobles were captured.
如今在此任凭我们处置
and are held here at our pleasure.
不过 诸位 还有更好的消息
But that, my lords, is not the end to our good news.
两日之前
Distracted by his grievous defeat,
苏格兰国王不堪惨败之痛
the King of the Scots took to his bed.
暴毙而亡
and died just two days ago.
同一日 他的妻子诞下唯一的子嗣
And on that day, his wife gave birth to their only child.
却非能继承王位的麟儿
And it was not the son and heir they had hoped for.
而是女婴
But a girl!
- 如此甚好 - 陛下
- Yes. Excellent. - Your Majesty,
此乃天助我也
I think we should see it as an act of divine intervention,
苏格兰王位将落于年轻女子之手
this passing of the Scottish crown to a very young female.
- 感谢上帝相助 - 诚心感谢上帝
- Thanks be to God. - Thanks be to God, indeed.
- 那是自然 - 这会是个美满的圣诞节
- Absolutely. - It shall be a very happy Christmas.
鉴于后位虚悬 我打算让玛丽公主
In the absence of a Queen I have asked the Lady Mary.
主持庆典
to preside over the festivities.
同时 王子将首次出席 履行职责
Also, my son will be performing his first public duties.
都退下吧
My Lords.
- 陛下 - 大人
- Your Majesty. - Sir.
- 臣告退 - 臣告退
- Majesty. - Your Majesty.
托马斯大人 有传言说
Sir Thomas. I was told you considered.
你认为我对萨里伯爵的处罚过轻
my treatment of the Earl of Surrey far too lenient.
你说对他的刑罚应当再重些
You said he deserved a greater punishment.
陛下 臣以为
Your Majesty, I thought…
有什么好想的
What business do you have to think?
若我是你 便不会再想
If I were you I would not think.
只怕深思会让我得出错误的结论
if thinking makes me come to the wrong conclusion.
- 退下 - 臣告退
- Get out, Tom. - Majesty.
- 你看上去真美 - 大人
- You look beautiful. - My Lord.
祝您圣诞快乐
May I wish you a very happy Christmas.
- 玛丽女士 - 凯瑟琳
- Lady Mary. - Catherine.
拉蒂默大人近来如何
How is Lord Latimer?
不太好 他还在病中 无法上朝
No better. He did not feel strong enough to come to court.
我为他伤心
I am so sad for him.
还有你 我为你们两人祈祷
And for you. I pray for both of you.
感谢您的关心
I thank you for that.
我会转达您的慰问之意
I will give him your good wishes,
- 圣诞快乐 - 圣诞快乐 凯瑟琳
- and Happy Christmas. - Happy Christmas, Catherine.
法国大使阁下到
His Excellency, the French Ambassador.
大使
Excellence.
玛丽女士
Lady Mary!
幸会
Enchanter!
我一直认为 你一定会是
I persist in thinking you would.
奥尔良公爵完美的新娘
make a perfect bride for the Duke of Orleans.
承您美言
I am honored that you think so.
我会将他的画像呈给您
I'll send you his picture.
爱德华王子和伊丽莎白女士驾到
Prince Edward and Lady Elizabeth.
爱德华 爱德华 别那么心急
Edward! Edward! Don't be so impatient.
赫福德伯爵和伯爵夫人
The Earl and Lady Hertford.
爱德华王子
Prince Edward.
大人们 请允许我向您们介绍
My Lords, may I present His Grace,
- 爱德华王子 - 大人
- Prince Edward. - My Lords.
- 殿下 - 欢迎您们在圣诞节时
- Your Grace. - You are most welcome.
造访我国
to His Majesty's court at this Christmas time.
能得殿下亲自关怀 实乃幸事
Your Grace is very kind to speak to us in person.
- 我一直学着做呐 - 做得好
- I have been practising. - Well done.
- 走吧 - 史考菲女士和戴维女士
- Now come. - Lady Scofield. Lady Davit.
大人 国王想向您提议
My Lords, the King has a proposal to put to you.
我们两国应签订和平条约
There should be a peace treaty between our countries…
也该为爱德华王子及新晋
and a formal betrothal between Prince Edward.
苏格兰的玛丽公主订立婚约
and the newly born Princess Mary of Scots.
德文伯爵
The Earl of Devon.
国王也意识到可能遇到的困难
The King is not unaware of possible… difficulties.
因此 如果得到你们的支持
Which is why, if you support the cause,
将会回以不菲的赏赐
you will be rewarded with a handsome pension.
也将被即可释放 返回苏格兰
and will be released at once to return to Scotland.
我想圣诞节之际
I am sure your families.
家人对各位定然甚是思念
are missing you greatly at this time of year.
将心比心 若让我和妻子分离
I know how I should feel,
的确痛苦非常
if I were separated from my own dear wife.
公爵大人 欢迎返回王庭
Your Grace. Welcome back to court.
公爵夫人没和您同行吗
Is the Duchess not with you?
没有 她…
No, she's…
内子随心而行
the Duchess does as she pleases.
我们各自生活 互不干涉
We live mostly separate lives.
很抱歉 我为您家庭和睦而祈祷
I'm very sorry. I… I will pray for your reconciliation.
韦斯福德伯爵
The Earl of Wexford.
陛下安好吗
How is the King?
如你所料 他郁郁寡欢
He has been melancholy as you might have supposed.
我想他对寻找生活之乐已然绝望
I think he despairs of finding any happiness in this life.
但前几周他突然情绪高涨
But in the last few weeks his mood has altogether changed.
不知道是怎么回事
Why, I cannot explain.
或许有感于苏格兰大捷
Triumph in Scotland, perhaps?
公主 臣告退
My Lady.
- 大人慢走 - 国王驾到
- Your Grace. - His Majesty the King!
- 陛下 - 陛下
- Your Majesty. - Your Majesty.
- 圣诞快乐 - 祝陛下圣诞快乐
- Merry Christmas. - Merry Christmas Your Majesty!
精彩
Bravo!
陛下
Majesty.
- 陛下 - 何事
- Your Majesty. - What is it?
拉蒂默夫人来向陛下请愿
The Lady Latimer is come to petition Your Majesty.
恳请陛下撤销对其夫君拉蒂默大人的
to lift the suspicion of treason from her husband,
- 叛国之罪 - 她现在何处
- Lord Latimer. - Where is she?
汤姆 这与你何干
What does any of this have to do with you, Tom?
回陛下 确与臣无关
Nothing, Your Majesty.
但臣乃其故友
Except that I'm a friend of the family.
我相信拉蒂默大人对陛下的忠心
I believe in Lord Latimer's complete loyalty to Your Majesty.
我觉得你是醉翁之意不在酒
I think your mind works another way.
另有目的 不 别急着否认
and to another purpose… No, no. Don't deny it!
这也怪不得你 她确实是位美人
Nor can I blame you. She is still a very handsome woman,
马上就会成为富有的寡妇
and soon to be a very rich widow.
带她来见我
Bring her to me.
- 见过陛下 - 汤姆
- Your Majesty. - Tom.
- 见过玛丽女士 - 大人
- Lady Mary. - My Lord.
我向阁下致歉
My apologies, Your Excellency.
最近我未在朝中
I have recently been away from court.
未能参与国事 大使 恕我失陪
and I am not privy to the King. Ambassador, excuse me.
公爵 朝中久未见您的身影
You've been a long time absent from court, Your Grace!
不过是打理我的产业去了 陛下
Only to tend to my estates, Your Majesty.
我以为你是对我避而不见呢
I rather thought you'd been careful of me.
你以为我还在生你的气
You imagine I'm still angry with you.
公爵 你多心了
You can be too careful, Your Grace.
公爵疏离君王多日
It is very remiss of you to.
实乃粗心之举啊
neglect your sovereign for so long.
陛下 臣明白
Yes, Your Majesty.
好了 我想让你为我做点事
Anyway, I want you to do something for me.
公爵大人
Your Grace!
- 我要见你家主人 - 抱歉 公爵大人
- I need to speak to your master. - Alas, Your Grace,
我家主人此刻卧病在床
my master is in bed with gout.
正受通风折磨
and in the greatest agony.
不 务必请公爵进来
No, no. Show His Grace in. By all means.
请公爵见谅
Your Grace must forgive me.
无妨
Of course.
我给你带来点东西
I have brought something for you.
请问上面所书何事
May I ask its import?
主要是我主之间秘密条约的相关事宜
It contains the outlines for a secret treaty between our masters.
关于近来英国商船
The recent seizures of English merchant ships.
在法国港口遭到扣押
in the French ports.
以及法王与土耳其
and the French King's new amity with the Turks.
新盟友关系的最终解决方案
are the final straw.
亨利国王许诺 无论何时 只要汝皇有难
King Henry promises to support the Emperor.
他必将鼎立相助
whenever he is called upon to do so.
他同时承诺会与汝皇的军队
He also pledges to invade France.
联合进攻法国
in conjunction with the Emperor's armies.
大人的这份密函实比治愈我痛风之疾的药方
Your Grace could not have made.
更令在下欣喜不已
me happier if you had brought me a cure for gout!
我会立即将此函呈递吾皇
I will make sure this is delivered to the Emperor immediately.
我敢肯定他收到此函后
and you can be sure that he will receive it.
定会非常高兴
with the very greatest pleasure.
陛下 拉蒂默女士到了
Your Majesty, Lady Latimer is here.
- 陛下 - 拉蒂默女士
- Your Majesty. - Lady Latimer.
拉蒂默女士 我向你保证
Lady Latimer, I wanted to assure you.
你的丈夫并没有叛国嫌疑
there is no suspicion of treason against your husband,
更不用说你和你的家族了
still less against you and your family.
谢谢您 陛下
Thank you, Your Majesty.
我十分清楚在这次北方叛乱期间
I know very well the cause of the distress to Lord Latimer.
拉蒂默亲王所遭劫难的缘由
during the late rebellion in the North.
我也知道你和你的继子惨遭
I also know that you and your stepchildren were.
叛党罗伯特·阿斯克一伙的虐待和凌辱
very roughly handled by the traitor Robert Aske.
那种经历一定令你惶恐万分 女士
You must have been very frightened, my Lady.
陛下 其实在当时
Well, at the time, sir,
更令我惶恐忧心的是 我的丈夫
I was more frightened for my husband,
我担心他的安危和精神状况
for his safety and his sanity.
我听闻拉蒂默大人近来体况欠佳
I hear that Lord Latimer is unwell.
他已病入膏肓 陛下
He is very ill indeed, Your Majesty.
恐怕已经时日无多
and not likely to live long.
- 你俩尚无子嗣吗 - 没有 陛下
- You have no children by him? - No, Your Majesty.
与你第一任丈夫也没有吗
Nor by your first husband?
也没有
Ah. No.
我十七岁便嫁与伯勒大人之子
I was married at seventeen to Edward Borough,
爱德华·伯勒
the son of Lord Borough.
但是婚后三年 他便亡故
But he died three years later.
我听说他是精神失常 是真的吗
I was told he was insane. Is it true?
那确非一段完满的婚姻 陛下
It was not a happy marriage, Your Majesty.
那段岁月定然不堪回首吧
Do you think such a thing exists?
当然
Oh, yes!
可我依然竭心尽力地去面对
I believe so with all my heart and soul.
请原谅我
Ah… please forgive me.
不 不
No, no, no, no, no.
拉蒂默女士 你这般乐观精神
You are to be congratulated, Lady Latimer,
着实值得赞佩
for your… eternal optimism.
大人
Your Grace,
陛下吩咐送此谕函 交您亲览
His Majesty has sent these papers for your attention.
谢谢 莱斯利先生
Thank you, Mr. Risley.
对了 莱斯利先生
Ah, Mr. Risley,
诚如你所知
You know I'm sure.
我确信陛下已和伟大的天主教宗国
that the King has made a secret treaty with the Emperor,
签订了一份秘密条约
the great champion of Catholicism!
可是为何没有看到陛下发令
Well, as a result, I see no reason why we should not start.
举国清剿路德会
hunting down all the Lutherans.
和新教徒呢
and evangelicals in His Majesty's Kingdom.
您觉得他们近来活动很猖獗吗
Do you think there are many such?
我确信如此
I know it!
他们衍续如鼠
They breed like rats.
所到之处 尽其所能播散恶毒的异端邪说
They spread the vile disease of their heresy everywhere!
并且就在当下 其中党羽
Some of them, even now,
已潜匿于君王之侧了
are very close to the King.
那我们应将其揪出并一举清除
And…we should flush them out?
没错
Exactly.
并将他们活活烧死在肮脏的肉市之中
And set them on the pyres at Smithfield.
你意下如何呢 莱斯利先生
Don't you agree, Mr. Risley?
是包裹吗 亲爱的
Parcels, sweetheart?
- 从何而来 - 从国王那里
- Who from? - From the King.
国王
The King?
来自国王的包裹吗
Parcels from the King?
你不想打开看看吗
Well. Are you not going to open them?
- 好吧 - 打开吧
- Yes… - Open them then.
是什么
What are they?
褶裥… 还有衣袖
Pleats… and sleeves.
一些服装衣饰
For dresses.
让我看看
Let me look.
- 都是华贵的服饰吗 - 是的
- Are they fashionable? - Yes.
国王为何要送你礼物
Why should the King send you presents?
我不知道 我觉得我应该退还回去
I don't know. I think that I should return them.
你不能退还国王的礼物
You cannot return presents to the King.
你必须收下并致谢
You must acknowledge them.
可我并不知道他为何要送我礼物
I don't know why he has sent them.
你知道 亲爱的
Yes you do, my love.
你心里清楚
Yes you do.
我此刻已与行尸走肉无异
I feel as though I am dead already.
以吾仁慈的陛下
I call upon His Gracious Majesty,
亨利八世之名
King Henry VIII,
于上帝及众位
to pledge before God.
证官近前宣誓
and these witnesses to honour.
恪守与神圣罗马帝国之皇
this new Treaty between His Majesty.
查理五世陛下所签订的条约
and King Charles V, the Holy Roman Emperor.
此份条约 明确规定缔约双方
This treaty of mutual assurance contains.
在即日起两年之内 共同承担
within it an obligation to undertake a war against France.
对法国进战的责任
within two years of this date,
为达成此项目标 吾王同意派遣
to which His Majesty agrees to send 40, 000 men-at-arms.
40000名战士出征
for that purpose.
陛下
Your Majesty,
您是否愿意宣誓
do you pledge to honour.
恪守此条约内的全部条款
all the terms of this new treaty?
我愿意 愿上帝保佑
I do, so help me God.
- 您是否愿意签署条约 - 我愿意
- Will you sign the Treaty? - I will.
你的部下终于能一览法国风光了
Finally. Your men shall see France.
这么说来 阁下
So Excellency,
罗马皇帝是当真要与英王
is it true that a new treaty has been signed.
签订这项新条约吗
between His Majesty and the Emperor!?
我实在不理解
I don't understand.
仅仅为了诛伐一个基督教国家
What, but the design of subjugating Christendom,
就能令之前还对英王的戮袭 而仇怨满腔的
could make a revengeful prince like the Emperor forget the insult.
罗马皇帝 顷刻便与之冰释前嫌吗
done to him by the King of England, in the person of his aunt?
既往不咎 马里亚克先生
Those insults are long forgotten, Monsieur Marillac.
那您也不否认 您家主人
You don't deny then, that your master plan is.
是意在征服整个基督教界
to subjugate the whole of Christendom?
何出此言
I do deny it.
那可是土耳其人的野心
I believe those ambitions are held by the Turks,
而您的主人却与他们为盟
with whom your own master is in alliance!
- 公爵大人 - 阁下 请允许我
- Your Grace. - Excellency! May I present you.
向贵国发出正式的战事宣告
with a formal intimation of war against your country.
拉蒂默女士到 托马斯爵士
Lady Latimer is here, Sir Thomas.
上帝啊 看看您
My God, look at you!
您看上去真美
You look so very beautiful.
凯瑟琳 怎么了
Catherine? What is it?
这身华服乃是他人相赠
This dress was a gift.
出自谁手
A gift? From whom?
国王陛下
From the King.
国王何时开始给您送礼物
When did the King start sending you presents?
就在最近 我并没有主动取悦于他
Recently. I… I gave him no cause!
是 当然不会 你怎么会
No. Of course not. How could you?
您是相信我的吧
Well, you do believe me, don't you?
请告诉我 您相信我
Please say that you believe me.
托马斯 我爱你
Thomas, I love you.
我从未想过从国王那儿得什么好处
I never sought these advances from the King,
而且从未有此意
Certainly do not welcome them.
是吗 你不想当英国的王后吗
You would not… like to be Queen of England?
不 看在老天的份上
No! For heavens' sake!
你很清楚那些王后的下场
You know what happens to his Queens!
人人都清楚
Everyone knows what happens.
托马斯 我害怕
Thomas, I… I'm afraid.
不要怕
Well, don't be.
他不过是寂寞了 挑逗你而已
He's just a lonely man that has set his cap at you.
希望如此
I hope so.
陛下明鉴 苏格兰摄政王后
Your Majesty should know that the Regent Queen of Scotland.
已准许就她的女儿玛丽
has given permission for negotiations to begin.
即未来的苏格兰女王
regarding a marriage contract.
与您的儿子 爱德华王子的
between her daughter Mary, soon to be Queen of Scots,
婚约事宜进行商讨
and your son, Prince Edward.
协商完成后 双方将签署条约
After the negotiations are complete a treaty.
英国与苏格兰的王座
will be signed, uniting through marriage.
将由此姻缘而连接
the English and Scottish thrones.
一如陛下所愿
as Your Majesty so desires.
看来我们的苏格兰老爷们总算就犯了
It seems our noble Scottish lords did as we bid them.
陛下 一个襁褓中的女王 一群多嘴多舌的贵族
Majesty, with an infant Queen, a quarrelsome nobility,
又少了法国撑腰 苏格兰人已走投无路
and a lack of French support, what choice do the Scots have?
我同意
I agree.
我只希望您加紧完成协商
I only ask you to expedite negotiations.
切勿错失良机
and not let this opportunity pass.
我始终不信任苏格兰人
I don't always trust the Scots.
- 主教阁下 您有何事要奏 - 陛下
- Your Grace… you tabled an item? - Your Majesty,
我很遗憾地告知您
I regret to have to inform you.
在您近旁存有一伙
that we have discovered a nest of heretics.
宗教异端分子在活动
at the very heart of Your Majesty's household.
您是说谁
Of whom do you speak?
王家礼拜堂的乐师们
The musicians of the Royal Chapel.
所有人吗
All of them?
唱诗班长官 约翰·玛贝克
The Master of Choristers, John Marbeck,
被指控是名秘密的加尔文教徒
stands accused of being a secret Calvinist.
还有风琴师罗伯特·特斯伍德以及埃德蒙·哈尔蒙
Also, the Organist, Robert Testwood and Edmund Harman,
那名歌手
a singing man.
陛下 您是否准许我
Do we have Your Majesty's permission.
逮捕并审问这几个人
to arrest and examine these men?
主教阁下 我准许
Your Grace, I give you licence.
我决不允许在我身边出现任何新教徒或者叛徒
I will have no evangelicals or traitors in this household.
对于那些企图改变或意图推动
And for those who wish to alter or push my Reformation.
我的革新去向极端的人 我要告诫他们
to the extremes, I say this:
只要我还活着 绝不允许英国发生任何
There will be no alteration to the Church of England.
教会改革
as long as I live!
约翰·玛贝克 罗伯特·特斯伍德
John Marbeck. Robert Testwood!
埃德蒙·哈尔蒙 你们全都被捕了
Edmund Harman! You are all under arrest.
抓住他
Seize him!
特斯伍德先生 您不该来这儿
You should not have come here, Mr. Testwood.
大人 我还能去哪儿 求求您救救我
My Lord… where else could I go? Please help me.
- 求您了 - 我无能为力
- I beg of you. - There is nothing I can do,
我不能冒险暴露自己
without condemning myself, and that I will not do.
您只需向加德纳告罪
You are only to be examined by Gardiner.
按他的要求去做
If you answer him as he desires to be answered,
- 您还有什么可怕的 - 我害怕 夫人
- then what have you to fear? - I fear, my Lady, that.
因为主教阁下又会诉诸其它教派
His Grace will then resort to other means of persuasion,
因为他现在正是这么做
since that is the way now.
那您应坚定您的信仰 特斯伍德先生
Then you must be strong in your faith, Mr. Testwood.
终有一天 我们都会走上耶稣之路
We all know the day may come when we have to walk.
但若我们心生恐惧 意念动摇
in the path of Christ. But if we are afraid, if we turn away,
就无权称自己为真正的基督徒
then we have no right to call ourselves true Christians.
您若胆敢提到我丈夫的名字
If you so much as mention my husband's name,
我向您保证 您家人的下场将十分凄惨
I assure you that things will go very badly with your family.
你美丽的妻子 还有那两个可爱的孩子
Your sweet wife and those two lovely children.
听说您贵体欠安 玛丽女士
People tell me that you have been unwell, Lady Mary.
我希望不妨事了吧
I trust not too unwell.
谢谢您
I thank you.
医师们给我放了一两次血
The surgeons have bled me once or twice,
我想应该好些了
and so I think to be better.
- 上帝保佑 - 是的 上帝保佑
- God willing. - Yes, God willing.
我的女士
My Lady.
跟我说说宫廷里的情况
Tell me what is happening in court.
国王又打算再娶了吗
Is the King thinking of marrying again?
最近颁布了一条新法律
There is a new law enacted.
规定任何国王可能婚娶的女士
It requires that any lady the King may marry must,
倘若受到任何对其行为不检的指控
on pain of death, disclose any charge.
将以死论处
of sexual misconduct that might be brought against her.
坦率的说 女士 这可大大缩小了范围
Frankly, my Lady, this rather narrows the field.
宫廷里的女士们 怎么说呢
The ladies at court are… how to say…
声誉都不太良好
not exactly known for their virtue.
我仍然认为国王想要再娶
I still think the King will want to remarry.
他的确已有子嗣
It is true he has a son,
但他还需要更多儿子以妨不虞
but he will need another son to feel secure,
- 以防长子不幸去世 - 您说得对
- in case the first should die. - You are right.
这个杀妻成性的国王
And yet… what woman on earth would want to marry a King.
还有谁敢与其成婚呢
who either puts his wives away-or kills them?
特斯伍德先生
Master Testwood.
我们在您家中搜到的异端邪说
Enough heretical material was discovered.
足以指控您为
in your house to have you condemned.
秘密的加尔文教徒
as a secret Calvinist.
不过 倘若你肯配合
However, I would fain save you,
我亦愿救你一命
but you must help me first.
掂量清楚
Just think.
现在这点痛
The pain you suffer now will be.
跟火刑比起来根本不值一提
as nothing compared to the pains of the fire.
而你此刻所遭之苦
And all because you falsely, mistakenly, treacherously.
都是因为你不识时务为上头的人遮掩
shelter those above you.
何不告诉招出他们的名字
If you will just confess to me their names.
快走
Move it on!
有一个叫菲利普·霍尔比的国王侍从
There is an usher of the King's, Sir Philip Holby.
是否也是异教徒
Is he one of your heretic circle?
- 不是 - 西蒙·海耶斯枢机主教
- No. - Dr. Simon Heynes,
他是不是呢
the Dean of Exeter?
我记得你为他唱过颂歌
You sang for him once, I think?
他是否也是秘密异教徒
Is he another of your secret heretics?
赫福德伯爵是否也参与此事呢
And what of the Earl of Hertford?
你若肯供出他
You give me the Earl of Hertford,
我就饶你一命
and I will give you back your life.
陛下圣明
An excellent plan, Your Majesty.
- 大人 - 女士
- My Lord. - My lady.
这是诸多故事中
Of all the hook stories,
- 我最喜欢的一个 您看呢 - 确实
- this is my favourite. Do you agree? - Indeed.
拉蒂默夫人 大人近况如何
How is your husband, Lady Latimer?
回陛下 还是卧床不起
I'm afraid he has taken to his bed, Your Majesty,
近日他已立下遗嘱
and lately made his will.
我深表遗憾
I am very sorry to hear that.
感谢陛下慷慨所赐衣物
I must thank Your Majesty for this beautiful dress,
和丰厚礼物
and your other generous gifts,
但我实在受之有愧
of which I have done nothing to deserve.
夫人整日愁眉紧锁
You looked very sad, my Lady.
我深知您近日处境艰难
I am sure your recent life has been very difficult for you.
因此赠予薄礼 宽慰汝心
I wanted to give you something to give you good cheer.
以期博您一笑
I wanted to see you smile.
如此甚好
There.
我们马上要和法国开战
We will soon be at war with France.
萨福克公爵 您意下如何
How is it, my Lord Suffolk?
陛下 臣以为此事不宜操之过急
It cannot come soon enough for me, Your Majesty.
正合我意
I agree.
此战一旦打响 这将是我等
When it comes, the war will be a chance for us to exceed.
超越先王亨利五世
even the glories of Henry V.
阿金库尔战役的良机
at Agincourt.
萨里大人 你有何高见
And you, my Lord Surrey?
陛下 微臣只求血洒疆场 勇立战功
Majesty, my kind always desires the honour of the field.
能征伐法国更是求之不得
And what better field than France?
附议
Aye.
拉蒂默夫人 你可会玩纸牌
Do you play cards, Lady Latimer?
回陛下 略懂一二
Yes, Your Majesty. I do.
甚好
Good.
国王似乎很是倾心于拉蒂默夫人
The King seems quite taken with Lady Latimer.
所言极是
It's true.
而据我们所知一旦国王迷上什么
And we know that when he takes a fancy to a person or a thing,
定会不择手段得到为止
he usually goes the whole way.
可能正是如此他才会这样好兴致吧
Perhaps that is why he's so happy.
大人
My Lord,
您可曾听说那些被抓的乐师们
have you heard what happened.
发生什么事了吗
to those musicians who were arrested?
加德纳提审了他们
Gardiner examined them.
而审讯结果不合他意
He was not satisfied with their answers.
所以三个乐师都被收押伦敦塔
and all three have been transferred to the Tower.
本官能否贸然问大人为何如此好奇此事
May I ask why Your Grace is curious?
当然 大人尽管问
Yes. You may ask.
失陪一下 哥哥
Excuse me, brother.
夫人 您手气太好
Your hand, my Lady.
这是给您的奖励
Your prize.
陛下 臣妾惶恐
No, Your Majesty.
- 请收下 - 陛下 我万不能收
- Please. - Your Majesty, I couldn't.
打开看看
Look inside.
陛下
Your Majesty,
臣妾万分欣喜
although I am so touched,
感激不尽
and flattered,
但这枚戒指臣妾实在受之不起
I cannot accept this ring.
看在寡人薄面 请务必收下
Please, accept this for me.
谢陛下隆恩
Thank you.
不必言谢
You're welcome.
托马斯大人
Sir Thomas!
- 我有美差派予你 - 陛下请讲
- I have some very good news for you. - Majesty?
我责成你前往布鲁塞尔
I'm sending you to Brussels,
永久出任我国驻荷兰摄政王府大使
on permanent embassy to the court of the Regent of the Netherlands.
托马斯大人 你可愿意
Does it please you, Sir Thomas?
微臣…
I'm…
微臣谢主隆恩
I'm very grateful to Your Majesty.
很好
Good.
陛下是否在考虑再立新后
Is Your Majesty considering another marriage?
可能吧
Perhaps.
- 还要筹划对法大战 - 当然
- And a war in France? - For certain.
陛下笃意再掀战火吗
Do you really want to fight again?
正是 你不想吗
Yes. Don't you?
我还以为你想
I thought you did.
- 还有再立新后 - 当然
- And… take another wife? - Yes.
我正值壮年
Am I not still able?
再立新后再续龙脉重振雄风
To have a wife? To have more children?
有何不可
To be myself?
愿大人灵魂永安
Requiem aeternum dona es Domine,
并以灵光承照
et lux perpetua au luceat.
约翰
John.
约翰 我有话对你说
John, I need to say something to you.
约翰
John.
你不得好死
Go to hell…
以圣父圣子圣灵的名义 阿门
In nomine Patris et Filii et Spiritus Sancti. Amen.
凯瑟琳·帕尔
Catherine Parr, we are sent here.
鉴于您亡夫孝期已满
by the King's Majesty to offer you,
国王陛下遂命我等前来
after your days of mourning for your late husband are complete,
代为提出求婚
his Majesty's hand in marriage.
天下粉黛 陛下唯独对您宠幸有加
His Majesty esteems you above all other women.
并期待您能接受陛下求婚
in his kingdom and hopes to find you well disposed.
如此一来
towards his offer, in which case.
陛下与您必将成为
he will be the happiest man now alive in England,
英格兰人人艳羡的神仙佳偶
and you the happiest woman.